<?xml-stylesheet href="/styles.css"?>
<div0 id="mice" type="book" subcorpus="ChiLit" filename="mice.txt">


<title>The Tale of Two Bad Mice</title>
<author>Beatrix Potter</author>
<p pid="1" id="mice.c0.p1"><s>[Illustration]</s> </p>

<div id="mice.1" subcorpus="ChiLit" booktitle="The Tale of Two Bad Mice" book="mice" type="chapter" num="1">
<title>BOOK 1.</title>
<p pid="1" id="mice.c1.p1"><s sid="1" id="mice.c1.s1">ONCE upon a time there was a very beautiful doll's-house; it was red brick with white windows, and it had real muslin curtains and a front door and a chimney.</s> </p>

<p pid="2" id="mice.c1.p2"><s sid="2" id="mice.c1.s2">IT belonged to two Dolls called Lucinda and Jane; at least it belonged to Lucinda, but she never ordered meals.</s> </p>

<p pid="3" id="mice.c1.p3"><s sid="3" id="mice.c1.s3">Jane was the Cook; but she never did any cooking, because the dinner had been bought ready-made, in a box full of shavings.</s> </p>

<p pid="4" id="mice.c1.p4"><s sid="4" id="mice.c1.s4">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="5" id="mice.c1.p5"><s sid="5" id="mice.c1.s5">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="6" id="mice.c1.p6"><s sid="6" id="mice.c1.s6">THERE were two red lobsters and a ham, a fish, a pudding, and some pears and oranges.</s> </p>

<p pid="7" id="mice.c1.p7"><s sid="7" id="mice.c1.s7">They would not come off the plates, but they were extremely beautiful.</s> </p>

<p pid="8" id="mice.c1.p8"><s sid="8" id="mice.c1.s8">ONE morning Lucinda and Jane had gone out for a drive in the doll's perambulator.</s> <s sid="9" id="mice.c1.s9">There was no one in the nursery, and it was very quiet.</s> <s sid="10" id="mice.c1.s10">Presently there was a little scuffling, scratching noise in a corner near the fire-place, where there was a hole under the skirting-board.</s> </p>

<p pid="9" id="mice.c1.p9"><s sid="11" id="mice.c1.s11">Tom Thumb put out his head for a moment, and then popped it in again.</s> </p>

<p pid="10" id="mice.c1.p10"><s sid="12" id="mice.c1.s12">Tom Thumb was a mouse.</s> </p>

<p pid="11" id="mice.c1.p11"><s sid="13" id="mice.c1.s13">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="12" id="mice.c1.p12"><s sid="14" id="mice.c1.s14">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="13" id="mice.c1.p13"><s sid="15" id="mice.c1.s15">A MINUTE afterwards, Hunca Munca, his wife, put her head out, too; and when she saw that there was no one in the nursery, she ventured out on the oilcloth under the coal-box.</s> </p>

<p pid="14" id="mice.c1.p14"><s sid="16" id="mice.c1.s16">THE doll's-house stood at the other side of the fire-place.</s> <s sid="17" id="mice.c1.s17">Tom Thumb and Hunca Munca went cautiously across the hearthrug.</s> <s sid="18" id="mice.c1.s18">They pushed the front door--it was not fast.</s> </p>

<p pid="15" id="mice.c1.p15"><s sid="19" id="mice.c1.s19">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="16" id="mice.c1.p16"><s sid="20" id="mice.c1.s20">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="17" id="mice.c1.p17"><s sid="21" id="mice.c1.s21">TOM THUMB and Hunca Munca went upstairs and peeped into the dining-room.</s> <s sid="22" id="mice.c1.s22">Then they squeaked with joy!</s> </p>

<p pid="18" id="mice.c1.p18"><s sid="23" id="mice.c1.s23">Such a lovely dinner was laid out upon the table!</s> <s sid="24" id="mice.c1.s24">There were tin spoons, and lead knives and forks, and two dolly-chairs--all _so_ convenient!</s> </p>

<p pid="19" id="mice.c1.p19"><s sid="25" id="mice.c1.s25">TOM THUMB set to work at once to carve the ham.</s> <s sid="26" id="mice.c1.s26">It was a beautiful shiny yellow, streaked with red.</s> </p>

<p pid="20" id="mice.c1.p20"><s sid="27" id="mice.c1.s27">The knife crumpled up and hurt him; he put his finger in his mouth.</s> </p>

<p pid="21" id="mice.c1.p21" type="speech"><s sid="28" id="mice.c1.s28"><qs/>"It is not boiled enough; it is hard.</s> <s sid="29" id="mice.c1.s29">You have a try, Hunca Munca."<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="22" id="mice.c1.p22"><s sid="30" id="mice.c1.s30">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="23" id="mice.c1.p23"><s sid="31" id="mice.c1.s31">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="24" id="mice.c1.p24"><s sid="32" id="mice.c1.s32">HUNCA MUNCA stood up in her chair, and chopped at the ham with another lead knife.</s> </p>

<p pid="25" id="mice.c1.p25" type="speech"><s sid="33" id="mice.c1.s33"><qs/>"It's as hard as the hams at the cheesemonger's,"<qe/> said Hunca Munca.</s> </p>

<p pid="26" id="mice.c1.p26"><s sid="34" id="mice.c1.s34">THE ham broke off the plate with a jerk, and rolled under the table.</s> </p>

<p pid="27" id="mice.c1.p27" type="speech"><s sid="35" id="mice.c1.s35"><qs/>"Let it alone,"<qe/><sss/> said Tom Thumb; <sse/><qs/>"give me some fish, Hunca Munca!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="28" id="mice.c1.p28"><s sid="36" id="mice.c1.s36">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="29" id="mice.c1.p29"><s sid="37" id="mice.c1.s37">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="30" id="mice.c1.p30"><s sid="38" id="mice.c1.s38">HUNCA MUNCA tried every tin spoon in turn; the fish was glued to the dish.</s> </p>

<p pid="31" id="mice.c1.p31"><s sid="39" id="mice.c1.s39">Then Tom Thumb lost his temper.</s> <s sid="40" id="mice.c1.s40">He put the ham in the middle of the floor, and hit it with the tongs and with the shovel--bang, bang, smash, smash!</s> </p>

<p pid="32" id="mice.c1.p32"><s sid="41" id="mice.c1.s41">The ham flew all into pieces, for underneath the shiny paint it was made of nothing but plaster!</s> </p>

<p pid="33" id="mice.c1.p33"><s sid="42" id="mice.c1.s42">THEN there was no end to the rage and disappointment of Tom Thumb and Hunca Munca.</s> <s sid="43" id="mice.c1.s43">They broke up the pudding, the lobsters, the pears and the oranges.</s> </p>

<p pid="34" id="mice.c1.p34"><s sid="44" id="mice.c1.s44">As the fish would not come off the plate, they put it into the red-hot crinkly paper fire in the kitchen; but it would not burn either.</s> </p>

<p pid="35" id="mice.c1.p35"><s sid="45" id="mice.c1.s45">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="36" id="mice.c1.p36"><s sid="46" id="mice.c1.s46">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="37" id="mice.c1.p37"><s sid="47" id="mice.c1.s47">TOM THUMB went up the kitchen chimney and looked out at the top--there was no soot.</s> </p>

<p pid="38" id="mice.c1.p38"><s sid="48" id="mice.c1.s48">WHILE Tom Thumb was up the chimney, Hunca Munca had another disappointment.</s> <s sid="49" id="mice.c1.s49">She found some tiny canisters upon the dresser, labelled--Rice--Coffee--Sago--but when she turned them upside down, there was nothing inside except red and blue beads.</s> </p>

<p pid="39" id="mice.c1.p39"><s sid="50" id="mice.c1.s50">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="40" id="mice.c1.p40"><s sid="51" id="mice.c1.s51">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="41" id="mice.c1.p41"><s sid="52" id="mice.c1.s52">THEN those mice set to work to do all the mischief they could--especially Tom Thumb!</s> <s sid="53" id="mice.c1.s53">He took Jane's clothes out of the chest of drawers in her bedroom, and he threw them out of the top floor window.</s> </p>

<p pid="42" id="mice.c1.p42"><s sid="54" id="mice.c1.s54">But Hunca Munca had a frugal mind.</s> <s sid="55" id="mice.c1.s55">After pulling half the feathers out of Lucinda's bolster, she remembered that she herself was in want of a feather bed.</s> </p>

<p pid="43" id="mice.c1.p43"><s sid="56" id="mice.c1.s56">WITH Tom Thumb's assistance she carried the bolster downstairs, and across the hearth-rug.</s> <s sid="57" id="mice.c1.s57">It was difficult to squeeze the bolster into the mouse-hole; but they managed it somehow.</s> </p>

<p pid="44" id="mice.c1.p44"><s sid="58" id="mice.c1.s58">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="45" id="mice.c1.p45"><s sid="59" id="mice.c1.s59">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="46" id="mice.c1.p46"><s sid="60" id="mice.c1.s60">THEN Hunca Munca went back and fetched a chair, a book-case, a bird-cage, and several small odds and ends.</s> <s sid="61" id="mice.c1.s61">The book-case and the bird-cage refused to go into the mouse-hole.</s> </p>

<p pid="47" id="mice.c1.p47"><s sid="62" id="mice.c1.s62">HUNCA MUNCA left them behind the coal-box, and went to fetch a cradle.</s> </p>

<p pid="48" id="mice.c1.p48"><s sid="63" id="mice.c1.s63">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="49" id="mice.c1.p49"><s sid="64" id="mice.c1.s64">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="50" id="mice.c1.p50"><s sid="65" id="mice.c1.s65">HUNCA MUNCA was just returning with another chair, when suddenly there was a noise of talking outside upon the landing.</s> <s sid="66" id="mice.c1.s66">The mice rushed back to their hole, and the dolls came into the nursery.</s> </p>

<p pid="51" id="mice.c1.p51"><s sid="67" id="mice.c1.s67">WHAT a sight met the eyes of Jane and Lucinda!</s> </p>

<p pid="52" id="mice.c1.p52"><s sid="68" id="mice.c1.s68">Lucinda sat upon the upset kitchen stove and stared; and Jane leant against the kitchen dresser and smiled--but neither of them made any remark.</s> </p>

<p pid="53" id="mice.c1.p53"><s sid="69" id="mice.c1.s69">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="54" id="mice.c1.p54"><s sid="70" id="mice.c1.s70">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="55" id="mice.c1.p55"><s sid="71" id="mice.c1.s71">THE book-case and the bird-cage were rescued from under the coal-box--but Hunca Munca has got the cradle, and some of Lucinda's clothes.</s> </p>

<p pid="56" id="mice.c1.p56"><s sid="72" id="mice.c1.s72">SHE also has some useful pots and pans, and several other things.</s> </p>

<p pid="57" id="mice.c1.p57"><s sid="73" id="mice.c1.s73">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="58" id="mice.c1.p58"><s sid="74" id="mice.c1.s74">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="59" id="mice.c1.p59" type="speech"><s sid="75" id="mice.c1.s75">THE little girl that the doll's-house belonged to, said,--<qs/>"I will get a doll dressed like a policeman!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="60" id="mice.c1.p60" type="speech"><s sid="76" id="mice.c1.s76">BUT the nurse said,--<qs/>"I will set a mouse-trap!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="61" id="mice.c1.p61"><s sid="77" id="mice.c1.s77">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="62" id="mice.c1.p62"><s sid="78" id="mice.c1.s78">SO that is the story of the two Bad Mice,--but they were not so very very naughty after all, because Tom Thumb paid for everything he broke.</s> </p>

<p pid="63" id="mice.c1.p63"><s sid="79" id="mice.c1.s79">He found a crooked sixpence under the hearthrug; and upon Christmas Eve, he and Hunca Munca stuffed it into one of the stockings of Lucinda and Jane.</s> </p>

<p pid="64" id="mice.c1.p64"><s sid="80" id="mice.c1.s80">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="65" id="mice.c1.p65"><s sid="81" id="mice.c1.s81">[Illustration]</s> </p>

<p pid="66" id="mice.c1.p66"><s sid="82" id="mice.c1.s82">AND very early every morning--before anybody is awake--Hunca Munca comes with her dust-pan and her broom to sweep the Dollies' house!</s> </p>

</div>


</div0>