<?xml-stylesheet href="/styles.css"?>
<div0 id="bunny" type="book" subcorpus="ChiLit" filename="bunny.txt">


<title>The Tale Of Benjamin Bunny</title>
<author>Beatrix Potter</author>
<div id="bunny.0" subcorpus="ChiLit" booktitle="The Tale Of Benjamin Bunny" book="bunny" type="chapter" num="0">
<title/>
<p pid="1" id="bunny.c0.p1"><s sid="1" id="bunny.c0.s1">FOR THE CHILDREN OF SAWREY</s> </p>

<p pid="2" id="bunny.c0.p2"><s sid="2" id="bunny.c0.s2">FROM OLD MR.</s> <s sid="3" id="bunny.c0.s3">BUNNY</s> </p>

</div>
<div id="bunny.1" subcorpus="ChiLit" booktitle="The Tale Of Benjamin Bunny" book="bunny" type="chapter" num="1">
<title>BOOK 1.</title>
<p pid="1" id="bunny.c1.p1"><s sid="1" id="bunny.c1.s1">One morning a little rabbit sat on a bank.</s> </p>

<p pid="2" id="bunny.c1.p2"><s sid="2" id="bunny.c1.s2">He pricked his ears and listened to the trit-trot, trit-trot of a pony.</s> </p>

<p pid="3" id="bunny.c1.p3"><s sid="3" id="bunny.c1.s3">A gig was coming along the road; it was driven by Mr. McGregor, and beside him sat Mrs. McGregor in her best bonnet.</s> </p>

<p pid="4" id="bunny.c1.p4"><s sid="4" id="bunny.c1.s4">As soon as they had passed, little Benjamin Bunny slid down into the road, and set off--with a hop, skip, and a jump--to call upon his relations, who lived in the wood at the back of Mr. McGregor's garden.</s> </p>

<p pid="5" id="bunny.c1.p5"><s sid="5" id="bunny.c1.s5">That wood was full of rabbit holes; and in the neatest, sandiest hole of all lived Benjamin's aunt and his cousins--Flopsy, Mopsy, Cotton-tail, and Peter.</s> </p>

<p pid="6" id="bunny.c1.p6"><s sid="6" id="bunny.c1.s6">Old Mrs. Rabbit was a widow; she earned her living by knitting rabbit-wool mittens and muffatees (I once bought a pair at a bazaar).</s> <s sid="7" id="bunny.c1.s7">She also sold herbs, and rosemary tea, and rabbit-tobacco (which is what we call lavender).</s> </p>

<p pid="7" id="bunny.c1.p7"><s sid="8" id="bunny.c1.s8">Little Benjamin did not very much want to see his Aunt.</s> </p>

<p pid="8" id="bunny.c1.p8"><s sid="9" id="bunny.c1.s9">He came round the back of the fir-tree, and nearly tumbled upon the top of his Cousin Peter.</s> </p>

<p pid="9" id="bunny.c1.p9"><s sid="10" id="bunny.c1.s10">Peter was sitting by himself.</s> <s sid="11" id="bunny.c1.s11">He looked poorly, and was dressed in a red cotton pocket-handkerchief.</s> </p>

<p pid="10" id="bunny.c1.p10" type="speech"><s sid="12" id="bunny.c1.s12"><qs/>"Peter,"<qe/><sls/> said little Benjamin, in a whisper, <sle/><qs/>"who has got your clothes?"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="11" id="bunny.c1.p11" type="speech"><s sid="13" id="bunny.c1.s13">Peter replied, <qs/>"The scarecrow in Mr. McGregor's garden,"<qe/> and described how he had been chased about the garden, and had dropped his shoes and coat.</s> </p>

<p pid="12" id="bunny.c1.p12"><s sid="14" id="bunny.c1.s14">Little Benjamin sat down beside his cousin and assured him that Mr. McGregor had gone out in a gig, and Mrs. McGregor also; and certainly for the day, because she was wearing her best bonnet.</s> </p>

<p pid="13" id="bunny.c1.p13"><s sid="15" id="bunny.c1.s15">Peter said he hoped that it would rain.</s> </p>

<p pid="14" id="bunny.c1.p14" type="speech"><s sid="16" id="bunny.c1.s16">At this point old Mrs. Rabbit's voice was heard inside the rabbit hole, calling:</s> <s sid="17" id="bunny.c1.s17"><qs/>"Cotton-tail!</s> <s sid="18" id="bunny.c1.s18">Cotton-tail! fetch some more camomile!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="15" id="bunny.c1.p15"><s sid="19" id="bunny.c1.s19">Peter said he thought he might feel better if he went for a walk.</s> </p>

<p pid="16" id="bunny.c1.p16"><s sid="20" id="bunny.c1.s20">They went away hand in hand, and got upon the flat top of the wall at the bottom of the wood.</s> <s sid="21" id="bunny.c1.s21">From here they looked down into Mr. McGregor's garden.</s> <s sid="22" id="bunny.c1.s22">Peter's coat and shoes were plainly to be seen upon the scarecrow, topped with an old tam-o'-shanter of Mr. McGregor's.</s> </p>

<p pid="17" id="bunny.c1.p17" type="speech"><s sid="23" id="bunny.c1.s23">Little Benjamin said:</s> <s sid="24" id="bunny.c1.s24"><qs/>"It spoils people's clothes to squeeze under a gate; the proper way to get in is to climb down a pear-tree."<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="18" id="bunny.c1.p18"><s sid="25" id="bunny.c1.s25">Peter fell down head first; but it was of no consequence, as the bed below was newly raked and quite soft.</s> </p>

<p pid="19" id="bunny.c1.p19"><s sid="26" id="bunny.c1.s26">It had been sown with lettuces.</s> </p>

<p pid="20" id="bunny.c1.p20"><s sid="27" id="bunny.c1.s27">They left a great many odd little footmarks all over the bed, especially little Benjamin, who was wearing clogs.</s> </p>

<p pid="21" id="bunny.c1.p21"><s sid="28" id="bunny.c1.s28">Little Benjamin said that the first thing to be done was to get back Peter's clothes, in order that they might be able to use the pocket-handkerchief.</s> </p>

<p pid="22" id="bunny.c1.p22"><s sid="29" id="bunny.c1.s29">They took them off the scarecrow.</s> <s sid="30" id="bunny.c1.s30">There had been rain during the night; there was water in the shoes, and the coat was somewhat shrunk.</s> </p>

<p pid="23" id="bunny.c1.p23"><s sid="31" id="bunny.c1.s31">Benjamin tried on the tam-o'-shanter, but it was too big for him.</s> </p>

<p pid="24" id="bunny.c1.p24"><s sid="32" id="bunny.c1.s32">Then he suggested that they should fill the pocket-handkerchief with onions, as a little present for his Aunt.</s> </p>

<p pid="25" id="bunny.c1.p25"><s sid="33" id="bunny.c1.s33">Peter did not seem to be enjoying himself; he kept hearing noises.</s> </p>

<p pid="26" id="bunny.c1.p26"><s sid="34" id="bunny.c1.s34">Benjamin, on the contrary, was perfectly at home, and ate a lettuce leaf.</s> <s sid="35" id="bunny.c1.s35">He said that he was in the habit of coming to the garden with his father to get lettuces for their Sunday dinner.</s> </p>

<p pid="27" id="bunny.c1.p27"><s sid="36" id="bunny.c1.s36">(The name of little Benjamin's papa was old Mr. Benjamin Bunny.)</s> </p>

<p pid="28" id="bunny.c1.p28"><s sid="37" id="bunny.c1.s37">The lettuces certainly were very fine.</s> </p>

<p pid="29" id="bunny.c1.p29"><s sid="38" id="bunny.c1.s38">Peter did not eat anything; he said he should like to go home.</s> <s sid="39" id="bunny.c1.s39">Presently he dropped half the onions.</s> </p>

<p pid="30" id="bunny.c1.p30"><s sid="40" id="bunny.c1.s40">Little Benjamin said that it was not possible to get back up the pear-tree with a load of vegetables.</s> <s sid="41" id="bunny.c1.s41">He led the way boldly towards the other end of the garden.</s> <s sid="42" id="bunny.c1.s42">They went along a little walk on planks, under a sunny, red brick wall.</s> </p>

<p pid="31" id="bunny.c1.p31"><s sid="43" id="bunny.c1.s43">The mice sat on their doorsteps cracking cherry-stones; they winked at Peter Rabbit and little Benjamin Bunny.</s> </p>

<p pid="32" id="bunny.c1.p32"><s sid="44" id="bunny.c1.s44">Presently Peter let the pocket-handkerchief go again.</s> </p>

<p pid="33" id="bunny.c1.p33"><s sid="45" id="bunny.c1.s45">They got amongst flower-pots, and frames, and tubs.</s> <s sid="46" id="bunny.c1.s46">Peter heard noises worse than ever; his eyes were as big as lolly-pops!</s> </p>

<p pid="34" id="bunny.c1.p34"><s sid="47" id="bunny.c1.s47">He was a step or two in front of his cousin when he suddenly stopped.</s> </p>

<p pid="35" id="bunny.c1.p35"><s sid="48" id="bunny.c1.s48">This is what those little rabbits saw round that corner!</s> </p>

<p pid="36" id="bunny.c1.p36"><s sid="49" id="bunny.c1.s49">Little Benjamin took one look, and then, in half a minute less than no time, he hid himself and Peter and the onions underneath a large basket....</s> </p>

<p pid="37" id="bunny.c1.p37"><s sid="50" id="bunny.c1.s50">The cat got up and stretched herself, and came and sniffed at the basket.</s> </p>

<p pid="38" id="bunny.c1.p38"><s sid="51" id="bunny.c1.s51">Perhaps she liked the smell of onions!</s> </p>

<p pid="39" id="bunny.c1.p39"><s sid="52" id="bunny.c1.s52">Anyway, she sat down upon the top of the basket.</s> </p>

<p pid="40" id="bunny.c1.p40"><s sid="53" id="bunny.c1.s53">She sat there for _five hours_.</s> </p>

<p pid="41" id="bunny.c1.p41"><s sid="54" id="bunny.c1.s54">*       *       *       *       *</s> </p>

<p pid="42" id="bunny.c1.p42"><s sid="55" id="bunny.c1.s55">I cannot draw you a picture of Peter and Benjamin underneath the basket, because it was quite dark, and because the smell of onions was fearful; it made Peter Rabbit and little Benjamin cry.</s> </p>

<p pid="43" id="bunny.c1.p43"><s sid="56" id="bunny.c1.s56">The sun got round behind the wood, and it was quite late in the afternoon; but still the cat sat upon the basket.</s> </p>

<p pid="44" id="bunny.c1.p44"><s sid="57" id="bunny.c1.s57">At length there was a pitter-patter, pitter-patter, and some bits of mortar fell from the wall above.</s> </p>

<p pid="45" id="bunny.c1.p45"><s sid="58" id="bunny.c1.s58">The cat looked up and saw old Mr. Benjamin Bunny prancing along the top of the wall of the upper terrace.</s> </p>

<p pid="46" id="bunny.c1.p46"><s sid="59" id="bunny.c1.s59">He was smoking a pipe of rabbit-tobacco, and had a little switch in his hand.</s> </p>

<p pid="47" id="bunny.c1.p47"><s sid="60" id="bunny.c1.s60">He was looking for his son.</s> </p>

<p pid="48" id="bunny.c1.p48"><s sid="61" id="bunny.c1.s61">Old Mr. Bunny had no opinion whatever of cats.</s> </p>

<p pid="49" id="bunny.c1.p49"><s sid="62" id="bunny.c1.s62">He took a tremendous jump off the top of the wall on to the top of the cat, and cuffed it off the basket, and kicked it into the greenhouse, scratching off a handful of fur.</s> </p>

<p pid="50" id="bunny.c1.p50"><s sid="63" id="bunny.c1.s63">The cat was too much surprised to scratch back.</s> </p>

<p pid="51" id="bunny.c1.p51"><s sid="64" id="bunny.c1.s64">When old Mr. Bunny had driven the cat into the greenhouse, he locked the door.</s> </p>

<p pid="52" id="bunny.c1.p52"><s sid="65" id="bunny.c1.s65">Then he came back to the basket and took out his son Benjamin by the ears, and whipped him with the little switch.</s> </p>

<p pid="53" id="bunny.c1.p53"><s sid="66" id="bunny.c1.s66">Then he took out his nephew Peter.</s> </p>

<p pid="54" id="bunny.c1.p54"><s sid="67" id="bunny.c1.s67">Then he took out the handkerchief of onions, and marched out of the garden.</s> </p>

<p pid="55" id="bunny.c1.p55"><s sid="68" id="bunny.c1.s68">When Mr. McGregor returned about half an hour later he observed several things which perplexed him.</s> </p>

<p pid="56" id="bunny.c1.p56"><s sid="69" id="bunny.c1.s69">It looked as though some person had been walking all over the garden in a pair of clogs--only the footmarks were too ridiculously little!</s> </p>

<p pid="57" id="bunny.c1.p57"><s sid="70" id="bunny.c1.s70">Also he could not understand how the cat could have managed to shut herself up _inside_ the greenhouse, locking the door upon the _outside_.</s> </p>

<p pid="58" id="bunny.c1.p58"><s sid="71" id="bunny.c1.s71">When Peter got home his mother forgave him, because she was so glad to see that he had found his shoes and coat.</s> <s sid="72" id="bunny.c1.s72">Cotton-tail and Peter folded up the pocket-handkerchief, and old Mrs. Rabbit strung up the onions and hung them from the kitchen ceiling, with the bunches of herbs and the rabbit-tobacco.</s> </p>

<p pid="59" id="bunny.c1.p59"><s sid="73" id="bunny.c1.s73">THE END</s> </p>

</div>


</div0>