<?xml-stylesheet href="/annotationOutput/styles.css"?>
<div0 id="jemima" type="book" subcorpus="ChiLit" filename="jemima.txt">


<title>The Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck</title>
<author>Beatrix Potter</author>
<div id="jemima.0" subcorpus="ChiLit" booktitle="The Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck" bookauthor="Beatrix Potter" book="jemima" type="chapter" num="0">
<qe/><title/>
<p pid="1" id="jemima.c0.p1"><s sid="1" id="jemima.c0.s1">A FARMYARD TALE FOR RALPH AND BETSY</s> </p>

<qs/></div>
<div id="jemima.1" subcorpus="ChiLit" booktitle="The Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck" bookauthor="Beatrix Potter" book="jemima" type="chapter" num="1">
<qe/><title>BOOK 1.</title>
<p pid="1" id="jemima.c1.p1"><s sid="1" id="jemima.c1.s1">What a funny sight it is to see a brood of ducklings with a hen!</s> </p>

<p pid="2" id="jemima.c1.p2"><s sid="2" id="jemima.c1.s2">--Listen to the story of Jemima Puddle-duck, who was annoyed because the farmer's wife would not let her hatch her own eggs.</s> </p>

<p pid="3" id="jemima.c1.p3" type="speech"><s sid="3" id="jemima.c1.s3">Her sister-in-law, Mrs. Rebeccah Puddle-duck, was perfectly willing to leave the hatching to some one else--<qs/>"I have not the patience to sit on a nest for twenty-eight days; and no more have you, Jemima.</s> <s sid="4" id="jemima.c1.s4">You would let them go cold; you know you would!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="4" id="jemima.c1.p4" type="speech"><s sid="5" id="jemima.c1.s5"><qs/>"I wish to hatch my own eggs; I will hatch them all by myself,"<qe/> quacked Jemima Puddle-duck.</s> </p>

<p pid="5" id="jemima.c1.p5"><s sid="6" id="jemima.c1.s6">She tried to hide her eggs; but they were always found and carried off.</s> </p>

<p pid="6" id="jemima.c1.p6"><s sid="7" id="jemima.c1.s7">Jemima Puddle-duck became quite desperate.</s> <s sid="8" id="jemima.c1.s8">She determined to make a nest right away from the farm.</s> </p>

<p pid="7" id="jemima.c1.p7"><s sid="9" id="jemima.c1.s9">She set off on a fine spring afternoon along the cart-road that leads over the hill.</s> </p>

<p pid="8" id="jemima.c1.p8"><s sid="10" id="jemima.c1.s10">She was wearing a shawl and a poke bonnet.</s> </p>

<p pid="9" id="jemima.c1.p9"><s sid="11" id="jemima.c1.s11">When she reached the top of the hill, she saw a wood in the distance.</s> </p>

<p pid="10" id="jemima.c1.p10"><s sid="12" id="jemima.c1.s12">She thought that it looked a safe quiet spot.</s> </p>

<p pid="11" id="jemima.c1.p11"><s sid="13" id="jemima.c1.s13">Jemima Puddle-duck was not much in the habit of flying.</s> <s sid="14" id="jemima.c1.s14">She ran downhill a few yards flapping her shawl, and then she jumped off into the air.</s> </p>

<p pid="12" id="jemima.c1.p12"><s sid="15" id="jemima.c1.s15">She flew beautifully when she had got a good start.</s> </p>

<p pid="13" id="jemima.c1.p13"><s sid="16" id="jemima.c1.s16">She skimmed along over the tree-tops until she saw an open place in the middle of the wood, where the trees and brushwood had been cleared.</s> </p>

<p pid="14" id="jemima.c1.p14"><s sid="17" id="jemima.c1.s17">Jemima alighted rather heavily, and began to waddle about in search of a convenient dry nesting-place.</s> <s sid="18" id="jemima.c1.s18">She rather fancied a tree-stump amongst some tall fox-gloves.</s> </p>

<p pid="15" id="jemima.c1.p15"><s sid="19" id="jemima.c1.s19">But--seated upon the stump, she was startled to find an elegantly dressed gentleman reading a newspaper.</s> </p>

<p pid="16" id="jemima.c1.p16"><s sid="20" id="jemima.c1.s20">He had black prick ears and sandy coloured whiskers.</s> </p>

<p pid="17" id="jemima.c1.p17" type="speech"><s sid="21" id="jemima.c1.s21"><qs/>"Quack?"<qe/><sls/> said Jemima Puddle-duck, with her head and her bonnet on one side--<sle/><qs/>"Quack?"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="18" id="jemima.c1.p18"><s sid="22" id="jemima.c1.s22">The gentleman raised his eyes above his newspaper and looked curiously at Jemima--</s> </p>

<p pid="19" id="jemima.c1.p19" type="speech"><s sid="23" id="jemima.c1.s23"><qs/>"Madam, have you lost your way?"<qe/> said he.</s> <s sid="24" id="jemima.c1.s24">He had a long bushy tail which he was sitting upon, as the stump was somewhat damp.</s> </p>

<p pid="20" id="jemima.c1.p20"><s sid="25" id="jemima.c1.s25">Jemima thought him mighty civil and handsome.</s> <s sid="26" id="jemima.c1.s26">She explained that she had not lost her way, but that she was trying to find a convenient dry nesting-place.</s> </p>

<p pid="21" id="jemima.c1.p21" type="speech"><s sid="27" id="jemima.c1.s27"><qs/>"Ah! is that so? indeed!"<qe/> said the gentleman with sandy whiskers, looking curiously at Jemima.</s> <s sid="28" id="jemima.c1.s28">He folded up the newspaper, and put it in his coat-tail pocket.</s> </p>

<p pid="22" id="jemima.c1.p22"><s sid="29" id="jemima.c1.s29">Jemima complained of the superfluous hen.</s> </p>

<p pid="23" id="jemima.c1.p23" type="speech"><s sid="30" id="jemima.c1.s30"><qs/>"Indeed! how interesting!</s> <s sid="31" id="jemima.c1.s31">I wish I could meet with that fowl.</s> <s sid="32" id="jemima.c1.s32">I would teach it to mind its own business!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="24" id="jemima.c1.p24" type="speech"><s sid="33" id="jemima.c1.s33"><qs/>"But as to a nest--there is no difficulty:</s> <s sid="34" id="jemima.c1.s34">I have a sackful of feathers in my wood-shed.</s> <s sid="35" id="jemima.c1.s35">No, my dear madam, you will be in nobody's way.</s> <s sid="36" id="jemima.c1.s36">You may sit there as long as you like,"<qe/> said the bushy long-tailed gentleman.</s> </p>

<p pid="25" id="jemima.c1.p25"><s sid="37" id="jemima.c1.s37">He led the way to a very retired, dismal-looking house amongst the fox-gloves.</s> </p>

<p pid="26" id="jemima.c1.p26"><s sid="38" id="jemima.c1.s38">It was built of faggots and turf, and there were two broken pails, one on top of another, by way of a chimney.</s> </p>

<p pid="27" id="jemima.c1.p27" type="speech"><s sid="39" id="jemima.c1.s39"><qs/>"This is my summer residence; you would not find my earth--my winter house--so convenient,"<qe/> said the hospitable gentleman.</s> </p>

<p pid="28" id="jemima.c1.p28"><s sid="40" id="jemima.c1.s40">There was a tumble-down shed at the back of the house, made of old soap-boxes.</s> <s sid="41" id="jemima.c1.s41">The gentleman opened the door, and showed Jemima in.</s> </p>

<p pid="29" id="jemima.c1.p29"><s sid="42" id="jemima.c1.s42">The shed was almost quite full of feathers--it was almost suffocating; but it was comfortable and very soft.</s> </p>

<p pid="30" id="jemima.c1.p30"><s sid="43" id="jemima.c1.s43">Jemima Puddle-duck was rather surprised to find such a vast quantity of feathers.</s> <s sid="44" id="jemima.c1.s44">But it was very comfortable; and she made a nest without any trouble at all.</s> </p>

<p pid="31" id="jemima.c1.p31"><s sid="45" id="jemima.c1.s45">When she came out, the sandy whiskered gentleman was sitting on a log reading the newspaper--at least he had it spread out, but he was looking over the top of it.</s> </p>

<p pid="32" id="jemima.c1.p32"><s sid="46" id="jemima.c1.s46">He was so polite, that he seemed almost sorry to let Jemima go home for the night.</s> <s sid="47" id="jemima.c1.s47">He promised to take great care of her nest until she came back again next day.</s> </p>

<p pid="33" id="jemima.c1.p33"><s sid="48" id="jemima.c1.s48">He said he loved eggs and ducklings; he should be proud to see a fine nestful in his wood-shed.</s> </p>

<p pid="34" id="jemima.c1.p34"><s sid="49" id="jemima.c1.s49">Jemima Puddle-duck came every afternoon; she laid nine eggs in the nest.</s> <s sid="50" id="jemima.c1.s50">They were greeny white and very large.</s> <s sid="51" id="jemima.c1.s51">The foxy gentleman admired them immensely.</s> <s sid="52" id="jemima.c1.s52">He used to turn them over and count them when Jemima was not there.</s> </p>

<p pid="35" id="jemima.c1.p35" type="speech"><s sid="53" id="jemima.c1.s53">At last Jemima told him that she intended to begin to sit next day--<qs/>"and I will bring a bag of corn with me, so that I need never leave my nest until the eggs are hatched.</s> <s sid="54" id="jemima.c1.s54">They might catch cold,"<qe/> said the conscientious Jemima.</s> </p>

<p pid="36" id="jemima.c1.p36"><s sid="55" id="jemima.c1.s55">"Madam, I beg you not to trouble yourself with a bag; I will provide oats.</s> <s sid="56" id="jemima.c1.s56">But before you commence your tedious sitting, I intend to give you a treat.</s> <s sid="57" id="jemima.c1.s57">Let us have a dinner-party all to ourselves!</s> </p>

<p pid="37" id="jemima.c1.p37" type="speech"><s sid="58" id="jemima.c1.s58"><qs/>"May I ask you to bring up some herbs from the farm-garden to make a savoury omelette?</s> <s sid="59" id="jemima.c1.s59">Sage and thyme, and mint and two onions, and some parsley.</s> <s sid="60" id="jemima.c1.s60">I will provide lard for the stuff--lard for the omelette,"<qe/> said the hospitable gentleman with sandy whiskers.</s> </p>

<p pid="38" id="jemima.c1.p38"><s sid="61" id="jemima.c1.s61">Jemima Puddle-duck was a simpleton: not even the mention of sage and onions made her suspicious.</s> </p>

<p pid="39" id="jemima.c1.p39"><s sid="62" id="jemima.c1.s62">She went round the farm-garden, nibbling off snippets of all the different sorts of herbs that are used for stuffing roast duck.</s> </p>

<p pid="40" id="jemima.c1.p40"><s sid="63" id="jemima.c1.s63">And she waddled into the kitchen, and got two onions out of a basket.</s> </p>

<p pid="41" id="jemima.c1.p41" type="speech"><s sid="64" id="jemima.c1.s64">The collie-dog Kep met her coming out, <qs/>"What are you doing with those onions?</s> <s sid="65" id="jemima.c1.s65">Where do you go every afternoon by yourself, Jemima Puddle-duck?"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="42" id="jemima.c1.p42"><s sid="66" id="jemima.c1.s66">Jemima was rather in awe of the collie; she told him the whole story.</s> </p>

<p pid="43" id="jemima.c1.p43"><s sid="67" id="jemima.c1.s67">The collie listened, with his wise head on one side; he grinned when she described the polite gentleman with sandy whiskers.</s> </p>

<p pid="44" id="jemima.c1.p44"><s sid="68" id="jemima.c1.s68">He asked several questions about the wood, and about the exact position of the house and shed.</s> </p>

<p pid="45" id="jemima.c1.p45"><s sid="69" id="jemima.c1.s69">Then he went out, and trotted down the village.</s> <s sid="70" id="jemima.c1.s70">He went to look for two fox-hound puppies who were out at walk with the butcher.</s> </p>

<p pid="46" id="jemima.c1.p46"><s sid="71" id="jemima.c1.s71">Jemima Puddle-duck went up the cart-road for the last time, on a sunny afternoon.</s> <s sid="72" id="jemima.c1.s72">She was rather burdened with bunches of herbs and two onions in a bag.</s> </p>

<p pid="47" id="jemima.c1.p47"><s sid="73" id="jemima.c1.s73">She flew over the wood, and alighted opposite the house of the bushy long-tailed gentleman.</s> </p>

<p pid="48" id="jemima.c1.p48"><s sid="74" id="jemima.c1.s74">He was sitting on a log; he sniffed the air, and kept glancing uneasily round the wood.</s> <s sid="75" id="jemima.c1.s75">When Jemima alighted he quite jumped.</s> </p>

<p pid="49" id="jemima.c1.p49" type="speech"><s sid="76" id="jemima.c1.s76"><qs/>"Come into the house as soon as you have looked at your eggs.</s> <s sid="77" id="jemima.c1.s77">Give me the herbs for the omelette.</s> <s sid="78" id="jemima.c1.s78">Be sharp!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="50" id="jemima.c1.p50"><s sid="79" id="jemima.c1.s79">He was rather abrupt.</s> <s sid="80" id="jemima.c1.s80">Jemima Puddle-duck had never heard him speak like that.</s> </p>

<p pid="51" id="jemima.c1.p51"><s sid="81" id="jemima.c1.s81">She felt surprised, and uncomfortable.</s> </p>

<p pid="52" id="jemima.c1.p52"><s sid="82" id="jemima.c1.s82">While she was inside she heard pattering feet round the back of the shed.</s> <s sid="83" id="jemima.c1.s83">Some one with a black nose sniffed at the bottom of the door, and then locked it.</s> </p>

<p pid="53" id="jemima.c1.p53"><s sid="84" id="jemima.c1.s84">Jemima became much alarmed.</s> </p>

<p pid="54" id="jemima.c1.p54"><s sid="85" id="jemima.c1.s85">A moment afterwards there were most awful noises--barking, baying, growls and howls, squealing and groans.</s> </p>

<p pid="55" id="jemima.c1.p55"><s sid="86" id="jemima.c1.s86">And nothing more was ever seen of that foxy-whiskered gentleman.</s> </p>

<p pid="56" id="jemima.c1.p56"><s sid="87" id="jemima.c1.s87">Presently Kep opened the door of the shed, and let out Jemima Puddle-duck.</s> </p>

<p pid="57" id="jemima.c1.p57"><s sid="88" id="jemima.c1.s88">Unfortunately the puppies rushed in and gobbled up all the eggs before he could stop them.</s> </p>

<p pid="58" id="jemima.c1.p58"><s sid="89" id="jemima.c1.s89">He had a bite on his ear and both the puppies were limping.</s> </p>

<p pid="59" id="jemima.c1.p59"><s sid="90" id="jemima.c1.s90">Jemima Puddle-duck was escorted home in tears on account of those eggs.</s> </p>

<p pid="60" id="jemima.c1.p60"><s sid="91" id="jemima.c1.s91">She laid some more in June, and she was permitted to keep them herself: but only four of them hatched.</s> </p>

<p pid="61" id="jemima.c1.p61"><s sid="92" id="jemima.c1.s92">Jemima Puddle-duck said that it was because of her nerves; but she had always been a bad sitter.</s> </p>

<qs/></div>


</div0>