<?xml-stylesheet href="/annotationOutput/styles.css"?>
<div0 id="squirrel" type="book" subcorpus="ChiLit" filename="squirrel.txt">


<title>The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin</title>
<author>Beatrix Potter</author>
<div id="squirrel.0" subcorpus="ChiLit" booktitle="The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin" bookauthor="Beatrix Potter" book="squirrel" type="chapter" num="0">
<qe/><title/>
<p pid="1" id="squirrel.c0.p1"><s sid="1" id="squirrel.c0.s1">A STORY FOR NORAH</s> </p>

<qs/></div>
<div id="squirrel.1" subcorpus="ChiLit" booktitle="The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin" bookauthor="Beatrix Potter" book="squirrel" type="chapter" num="1">
<qe/><title>BOOK 1.</title>
<p pid="1" id="squirrel.c1.p1"><s sid="1" id="squirrel.c1.s1">This is a Tale about a tail--a tail that belonged to a little red squirrel, and his name was Nutkin.</s> </p>

<p pid="2" id="squirrel.c1.p2"><s sid="2" id="squirrel.c1.s2">He had a brother called Twinkleberry, and a great many cousins: they lived in a wood at the edge of a lake.</s> </p>

<p pid="3" id="squirrel.c1.p3"><s sid="3" id="squirrel.c1.s3">In the middle of the lake there is an island covered with trees and nut bushes; and amongst those trees stands a hollow oak-tree, which is the house of an owl who is called Old Brown.</s> </p>

<p pid="4" id="squirrel.c1.p4"><s sid="4" id="squirrel.c1.s4">One autumn when the nuts were ripe, and the leaves on the hazel bushes were golden and green--Nutkin and Twinkleberry and all the other little squirrels came out of the wood, and down to the edge of the lake.</s> </p>

<p pid="5" id="squirrel.c1.p5"><s sid="5" id="squirrel.c1.s5">They made little rafts out of twigs, and they paddled away over the water to Owl Island to gather nuts.</s> </p>

<p pid="6" id="squirrel.c1.p6"><s sid="6" id="squirrel.c1.s6">Each squirrel had a little sack and a large oar, and spread out his tail for a sail.</s> </p>

<p pid="7" id="squirrel.c1.p7"><s sid="7" id="squirrel.c1.s7">They also took with them an offering of three fat mice as a present for Old Brown, and put them down upon his door-step.</s> </p>

<p pid="8" id="squirrel.c1.p8"><s sid="8" id="squirrel.c1.s8">Then Twinkleberry and the other little squirrels each made a low bow, and said politely--</s> </p>

<p pid="9" id="squirrel.c1.p9" type="speech"><s sid="9" id="squirrel.c1.s9"><qs/>"Old Mr. Brown, will you favour us with permission to gather nuts upon your island?"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="10" id="squirrel.c1.p10"><s sid="10" id="squirrel.c1.s10">But Nutkin was excessively impertinent in his manners.</s> <s sid="11" id="squirrel.c1.s11">He bobbed up and down like a little red _cherry_, singing--</s> </p>

<p pid="11" id="squirrel.c1.p11" type="speech"><s sid="12" id="squirrel.c1.s12"><qs/>"Riddle me, riddle me, rot-tot-tote!</s> <s sid="13" id="squirrel.c1.s13">A little wee man, in a red red coat!</s> <s sid="14" id="squirrel.c1.s14">A staff in his hand, and a stone in his throat; If you'll tell me this riddle, I'll give you a groat."<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="12" id="squirrel.c1.p12"><s sid="15" id="squirrel.c1.s15">Now this riddle is as old as the hills; Mr. Brown paid no attention whatever to Nutkin.</s> </p>

<p pid="13" id="squirrel.c1.p13"><s sid="16" id="squirrel.c1.s16">He shut his eyes obstinately and went to sleep.</s> </p>

<p pid="14" id="squirrel.c1.p14"><s sid="17" id="squirrel.c1.s17">The squirrels filled their little sacks with nuts, and sailed away home in the evening.</s> </p>

<p pid="15" id="squirrel.c1.p15"><s sid="18" id="squirrel.c1.s18">But next morning they all came back again to Owl Island; and Twinkleberry and the others brought a fine fat mole, and laid it on the stone in front of Old Brown's doorway, and said--</s> </p>

<p pid="16" id="squirrel.c1.p16" type="speech"><s sid="19" id="squirrel.c1.s19"><qs/>"Mr. Brown, will you favour us with your gracious permission to gather some more nuts?"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="17" id="squirrel.c1.p17"><s sid="20" id="squirrel.c1.s20">But Nutkin, who had no respect, began to dance up and down, tickling old Mr. Brown with a _nettle_ and singing--</s> </p>

<p pid="18" id="squirrel.c1.p18" type="speech"><s sid="21" id="squirrel.c1.s21"><qs/>"Old Mr. B!</s> <s sid="22" id="squirrel.c1.s22">Riddle-me-ree!</s> <s sid="23" id="squirrel.c1.s23">Hitty Pitty within the wall, Hitty Pitty without the wall; If you touch Hitty Pitty, Hitty Pitty will bite you!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="19" id="squirrel.c1.p19"><s sid="24" id="squirrel.c1.s24">Mr. Brown woke up suddenly and carried the mole into his house.</s> </p>

<p pid="20" id="squirrel.c1.p20"><s sid="25" id="squirrel.c1.s25">He shut the door in Nutkin's face.</s> <s sid="26" id="squirrel.c1.s26">Presently a little thread of blue _smoke_ from a wood fire came up from the top of the tree, and Nutkin peeped through the key-hole and sang--</s> </p>

<p pid="21" id="squirrel.c1.p21" type="speech"><s sid="27" id="squirrel.c1.s27"><qs/>"A house full, a hole full!</s> <s sid="28" id="squirrel.c1.s28">And you cannot gather a bowl-full!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="22" id="squirrel.c1.p22"><s sid="29" id="squirrel.c1.s29">The squirrels searched for nuts all over the island and filled their little sacks.</s> </p>

<p pid="23" id="squirrel.c1.p23"><s sid="30" id="squirrel.c1.s30">But Nutkin gathered oak-apples--yellow and scarlet--and sat upon a beech-stump playing marbles, and watching the door of old Mr. Brown.</s> </p>

<p pid="24" id="squirrel.c1.p24"><s sid="31" id="squirrel.c1.s31">On the third day the squirrels got up very early and went fishing; they caught seven fat minnows as a present for Old Brown.</s> </p>

<p pid="25" id="squirrel.c1.p25"><s sid="32" id="squirrel.c1.s32">They paddled over the lake and landed under a crooked chestnut tree on Owl Island.</s> </p>

<p pid="26" id="squirrel.c1.p26"><s sid="33" id="squirrel.c1.s33">Twinkleberry and six other little squirrels each carried a fat minnow; but Nutkin, who had no nice manners, brought no present at all.</s> <s sid="34" id="squirrel.c1.s34">He ran in front, singing--</s> </p>

<p pid="27" id="squirrel.c1.p27" type="speech"><s sid="35" id="squirrel.c1.s35"><qs/>"The man in the wilderness said to me, <alt-qs/>'How many strawberries grow in the sea?'<alt-qe/></s> <s sid="36" id="squirrel.c1.s36">I answered him as I thought good-- 'As many red herrings as grow in the wood.'"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="28" id="squirrel.c1.p28"><s sid="37" id="squirrel.c1.s37">But old Mr. Brown took no interest in riddles--not even when the answer was provided for him.</s> </p>

<p pid="29" id="squirrel.c1.p29"><s sid="38" id="squirrel.c1.s38">On the fourth day the squirrels brought a present of six fat beetles, which were as good as plums in _plum-pudding_ for Old Brown.</s> <s sid="39" id="squirrel.c1.s39">Each beetle was wrapped up carefully in a dock-leaf, fastened with a pine-needle pin.</s> </p>

<p pid="30" id="squirrel.c1.p30"><s sid="40" id="squirrel.c1.s40">But Nutkin sang as rudely as ever--</s> </p>

<p pid="31" id="squirrel.c1.p31" type="speech"><s sid="41" id="squirrel.c1.s41"><qs/>"Old Mr. B! riddle-me-ree Flour of England, fruit of Spain, Met together in a shower of rain; Put in a bag tied round with a string, If you'll tell me this riddle, I'll give you a ring!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="32" id="squirrel.c1.p32"><s sid="42" id="squirrel.c1.s42">Which was ridiculous of Nutkin, because he had not got any ring to give to Old Brown.</s> </p>

<p pid="33" id="squirrel.c1.p33"><s sid="43" id="squirrel.c1.s43">The other squirrels hunted up and down the nut bushes; but Nutkin gathered robin's pincushions off a briar bush, and stuck them full of pine-needle pins.</s> </p>

<p pid="34" id="squirrel.c1.p34"><s sid="44" id="squirrel.c1.s44">On the fifth day the squirrels brought a present of wild honey; it was so sweet and sticky that they licked their fingers as they put it down upon the stone.</s> <s sid="45" id="squirrel.c1.s45">They had stolen it out of a bumble _bees'_ nest on the tippitty top of the hill.</s> </p>

<p pid="35" id="squirrel.c1.p35"><s sid="46" id="squirrel.c1.s46">But Nutkin skipped up and down, singing--</s> </p>

<p pid="36" id="squirrel.c1.p36" type="speech"><s sid="47" id="squirrel.c1.s47"><qs/>"Hum-a-bum! buzz! buzz!</s> <s sid="48" id="squirrel.c1.s48">Hum-a-bum buzz!</s> <s sid="49" id="squirrel.c1.s49">As I went over Tipple-tine I met a flock of bonny swine; Some yellow-nacked, some yellow backed!</s> <s sid="50" id="squirrel.c1.s50">They were the very bonniest swine That e'er went over Tipple-tine."<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="37" id="squirrel.c1.p37"><s sid="51" id="squirrel.c1.s51">Old Mr. Brown turned up his eyes in disgust at the impertinence of Nutkin.</s> </p>

<p pid="38" id="squirrel.c1.p38"><s sid="52" id="squirrel.c1.s52">But he ate up the honey!</s> </p>

<p pid="39" id="squirrel.c1.p39"><s sid="53" id="squirrel.c1.s53">The squirrels filled their little sacks with nuts.</s> </p>

<p pid="40" id="squirrel.c1.p40"><s sid="54" id="squirrel.c1.s54">But Nutkin sat upon a big flat rock, and played ninepins with a crab apple and green fir-cones.</s> </p>

<p pid="41" id="squirrel.c1.p41"><s sid="55" id="squirrel.c1.s55">On the sixth day, which was Saturday, the squirrels came again for the last time; they brought a new-laid _egg_ in a little rush basket as a last parting present for Old Brown.</s> </p>

<p pid="42" id="squirrel.c1.p42"><s sid="56" id="squirrel.c1.s56">But Nutkin ran in front laughing, and shouting--</s> </p>

<p pid="43" id="squirrel.c1.p43" type="speech"><s sid="57" id="squirrel.c1.s57"><qs/>"Humpty Dumpty lies in the beck, With a white counterpane round his neck, Forty doctors and forty wrights, Cannot put Humpty Dumpty to rights!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="44" id="squirrel.c1.p44"><s sid="58" id="squirrel.c1.s58">Now old Mr. Brown took an interest in eggs; he opened one eye and shut it again.</s> <s sid="59" id="squirrel.c1.s59">But still he did not speak.</s> </p>

<p pid="45" id="squirrel.c1.p45"><s sid="60" id="squirrel.c1.s60">Nutkin became more and more impertinent--</s> </p>

<p pid="46" id="squirrel.c1.p46" type="speech"><s sid="61" id="squirrel.c1.s61"><qs/>"Old Mr. B!</s> <s sid="62" id="squirrel.c1.s62">Old Mr. B!</s> <s sid="63" id="squirrel.c1.s63">Hickamore, Hackamore, on the King's kitchen door; All the King's horses, and all the King's men, Couldn't drive Hickamore, Hackamore, Off the King's kitchen door."<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="47" id="squirrel.c1.p47"><s sid="64" id="squirrel.c1.s64">Nutkin danced up and down like a _sunbeam_; but still Old Brown said nothing at all.</s> </p>

<p pid="48" id="squirrel.c1.p48"><s sid="65" id="squirrel.c1.s65">Nutkin began again--</s> </p>

<p pid="49" id="squirrel.c1.p49" type="speech"><s sid="66" id="squirrel.c1.s66"><qs/>"Arthur O'Bower has broken his band, He comes roaring up the land!</s> <s sid="67" id="squirrel.c1.s67">The King of Scots with all his power, Cannot turn Arthur of the Bower!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="50" id="squirrel.c1.p50"><s sid="68" id="squirrel.c1.s68">Nutkin made a whirring noise to sound like the _wind_, and he took a running jump right onto the head of Old Brown!...</s> </p>

<p pid="51" id="squirrel.c1.p51" type="speech"><s sid="69" id="squirrel.c1.s69">Then all at once there was a flutterment and a scufflement and a loud <qs/>"Squeak!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="52" id="squirrel.c1.p52"><s sid="70" id="squirrel.c1.s70">The other squirrels scuttered away into the bushes.</s> </p>

<p pid="53" id="squirrel.c1.p53"><s sid="71" id="squirrel.c1.s71">When they came back very cautiously, peeping round the tree--there was Old Brown sitting on his door-step, quite still, with his eyes closed, as if nothing had happened.</s> </p>

<p pid="54" id="squirrel.c1.p54"><s sid="72" id="squirrel.c1.s72">*       *       *       *       *</s> </p>

<p pid="55" id="squirrel.c1.p55"><s sid="73" id="squirrel.c1.s73">_But Nutkin was in his waistcoat pocket!_</s> </p>

<p pid="56" id="squirrel.c1.p56"><s sid="74" id="squirrel.c1.s74">This looks like the end of the story; but it isn't.</s> </p>

<p pid="57" id="squirrel.c1.p57"><s sid="75" id="squirrel.c1.s75">Old Brown carried Nutkin into his house, and held him up by the tail, intending to skin him; but Nutkin pulled so very hard that his tail broke in two, and he dashed up the staircase and escaped out of the attic window.</s> </p>

<p pid="58" id="squirrel.c1.p58"><s sid="76" id="squirrel.c1.s76">And to this day, if you meet Nutkin up a tree and ask him a riddle, he will throw sticks at you, and stamp his feet and scold, and shout--</s> </p>

<p pid="59" id="squirrel.c1.p59" type="speech"><s sid="77" id="squirrel.c1.s77"><qs/>"Cuck-cuck-cuck-cur-r-r-cuck-k-k!"<qe/></s> </p>

<p pid="60" id="squirrel.c1.p60"><s sid="78" id="squirrel.c1.s78">THE END</s> </p>

<qs/></div>


</div0>